All right, good afternoon, everybody.
Welcome, good to see you.
Hope you all have started your attack labs.
Everybody started?
Be a good time to start, I think.
Anyway, I hope you're enjoying it.
That's a new one this semester that's, I think,
really interesting and modern and current.
Okay, today we're going to talk about something
called the memory hierarchy.
Now, so far in the class, we've thought
We've thought of memory when we're looking at our assembly language programs, we've thought of memory as an array of bytes, just a big array of bytes that we can access with an index called an address.
But in actuality, the memory system is a very complex hierarchy of devices that provides this abstraction of this large linear array.
And so today we're going to look at how memory hierarchies are built.
and why they're built the way they are.
And what we'll see is that this sort of beautiful confluence of the properties of storage devices
and the properties of programs come together to create this beautiful design called a memory hierarchy.
So we're going to quickly kind of do a high-level tour of storage technologies and trends.
we're not going to go into a whole lot of detail.
The point in looking at these properties of these technologies is that there are some fundamental
properties that determine their performance and their speed, determine limits on their performance
and speed.
And so I want you to have, you know, just some high-level idea of what those properties are.
And then we'll look at a property of programs called locality of reference.
And we'll see how that locality and the properties of storage devices come together to suggest this design of memory systems as a hierarchy.
Okay, so we'll look at memories first.
Now, the workhorse memory is called a random access memory or RAM.
It's traditionally packaged up as a chip, and then you put multiple chips together to form, to form your main memory.
And there's a basic storage unit called a cell, which where each system,
cells stores one bit.
Okay, now there's, there's a RAM comes in two varieties.
There's S-RAM and D-RAM, and they're distinguished by the way that those cells are implemented.
So in an S-RAM requires, it's more complex than D-RAM.
It requires like four to six transistors per bit, whereas D-RAM only requires one transistor.
Okay, so you'll see that S-Rams are going to be more expensive.
be more expensive, lots more expensive, because they're more complex.
Each cell is more complex. But they're also much faster, like 10 order of magnitude faster than
DRAMs. And they have, there's some other properties too, like S-RAM constantly,
D-RAM constantly needs to be refreshed. If you don't hit it with a, with a voltage, with a voltage, it
loses the charge whereas DRAM, while it needs to be plugged in and have
an electric charge, it doesn't need to be refreshed, S-RAMs a lot more reliable than D-RAMs, so
there's less need for error detection and correction.
And so because of this difference, right, the S-Rams are costlier, smaller, and faster than D-Rams,
we find S-Rams being used in these small, fast memory.
on chip called cache memories.
And we're going to learn all about those on Thursday.
And then DRAM is the workhorse used in main memories,
and the frame buffers associated with graphics cards.
Now, DRAM and SRAM are volatile in the sense that if
they're powered off, they lose all the information.
So this is why when you turn your computer off, you have to, you lose
everything in your memory and you have to, when you turn it back on, you have to sort of reload
everything from your disk.
There's a different, another kind of memory called a non-volatile memory, which retains its information
when it's powered off.
And there's a whole bunch of these things, so-called read-only memories.
So the generic name for these non-volatile memories is read-only memories or ROMs, and
there's a whole bunch of different kinds sort of going back.
in time.
The original read-only memories were ROMs, and they can only be programmed once when the chip
was produced.
And then over time, gradually, over a period of like 20 or 30 years, there were improvements in the way that
ROMs could be programmed and in how they were erased, so they could be reprogrammed.
What we have today, the modern form of read-only memories, is called flash memory, which provides
the capability of...
of erasing, you can erase just chunks of the flash memory called blocks.
And then the the downside is that these things wear out after about 100,000 erasures.
Okay, so you can erase and reprogram 100,000 times and then it's you're bricked.
Now that these non-volatile memories are show up in, so-called firmware, which is a
software that's programmed into a ROM.
And you see those in the BIOS of computers.
So when you power on your computer, the very first instructions that execute are stored in a ROM, right?
If you're wondered, like, where do those things come from?
So they're stored in a ROM.
And then there's a boot process where gradually more and more information is,
and instructions are loaded into memory.
You know, IO devices have little computers in them.
in them call controllers.
These controllers consist of instructions and data that are stored in ROMs.
And you see them all over the place in these solid-state disks that, to the system look like a rotating disk,
but they're built of flash memories.
And these are, you see these in thumb drives, smartphones, tablets, and laptops, and they're even starting
to show up in servers now.
servers now.
So the memories are connected to the CPU using wires that are collectively called buses.
Okay, so data flows across the wires back and forth from the, we have the CPU chip,
and it consists of a register file.
These are the general purpose registers, RAX, RDI, and so on.
And there's an arithmetic logic unit that reads and writes data from the register files
and then manipulates that data in some way by doing some kind of arithmetic operation or some logical operation.
And if instructions need to access memory, so if there's, you're doing a move, a move instruction that reads or writes to memory, then that's handled by a bus interface, which is connected to a, what we'll call a system bus bus, and then that's connected to an I.O bridge and
This is another collection of chips.
Intel calls this, what I'm calling the I.O. Bridge, they call the chip set.
Okay, but it's a collection of chips separate from the CPU chip,
and then the I.O. Bridge is connected to another bus called the memory bus,
which connects the main memory.
Okay, now this is kind of an abstraction.
I don't want you to take this too literally, but it gives you the idea of how information flows in the system.
Okay.
modern systems use proprietary bus designs and they're very very arcane and increasingly
complex so we're just going to we're just going to use a fairly simple abstraction for for
these for these bus architectures now when us now suppose you do a load operation
like move move move cube the the eight bytes at address a into our a x okay so we call
that a load because we're we're loading from from the point of view of the CPU we're
loading data into the CPU, or we're loading data from memory into the CPU.
So when the CPU executes a move instruction like this, it first places the address of A on the memory bus,
and then the main memory senses that address and it reads the contents, the 8 bytes at address A.
So it retrieves the word, uh, 8 byte word from address A and places it back on the bus.
back on the bus.
Those bits travel through the I-O bridge to the bus interface.
And then the CPU reads the data word X from the data word X from the bus and then copies it into
register RAX.
Okay, so it's, now writing is, is, is similar.
Again, so here we're doing a move instruction, move Q from RAX into address A and main memory.
Okay.
If the CPU starts as before by placing the address A on the bus, main memory reads that address and then it waits for the data to arrive on the bus.
So the CPU then places the contents of RAX on the bus and those contents travel across to main memory, which then reads the, reads that word from the bus and stores it at address A.
Okay, so the point of all this is that operations that operations that occur, you know, reads and writes of registers,
Because the register files very close to the ALU, these happen in, on the order of a few cycles.
Okay, register, the register is very close to the, to the ALU.
So those operations are very, uh, happened very quickly.
Whereas memories actually, this is a set of chips that are very far away, relatively speaking, from the CPU.
And there's a lot going on in when you, if you have to read or write memory, there's, you have to do
multiple operations on the bus, data has to travel, propagate across that bus.
All this stuff takes time. So memory operations, reads and writes, are typically, you know, maybe
50 nanoseconds, 100 nanoseconds, whereas operations that occur between registers are
sub nanosecond. Okay. Okay. So, so you're talking about a one to two orders of
magnitude difference if you have to go off chip to retrieve something from memory.
Okay, so that's the first sort of big takeaway item about memory systems.
Now, another popular storage technology is rotating disks, and I don't know if you've ever torn one apart,
they're kind of interesting. There's a series of platters.
Each platters is coated with a magnetic material, and then bits, ones and zeros, are encoded in that
in that magnetic material. And then there's this arm that, ones and zeros, are encoded in that magnetic material.
And then there's this arm that can, it's, it's hinged right here, and then it can, it can, it can, it floats over the platter.
So it floats on a thin layer of air over the platter, and there's a reed right hat at the very end that can sense the changes in the magnetic field that encode the bits.
Okay.
So these platters are spinning around like, like, like, counterclockwise like this, and this arm can go back and forth.
So there's a lot of mechanical gear, so that this is a lot of,
all mechanical. So the mechanical nature of a rotating disk means it's going to be slower,
right, than D-Rams and S-Rams. And there's also electronics, like, it's like, it's like a little computer
in firmware that, that actually controls the operation of this drive, like controls how this
arm goes back and forth and, and, and controls how the data is read off of the, the read right-head.
So just in a little more detail, we can think of these disks consists of platters.
Each platter has two surfaces, the top and a bottom.
And then each surface consists of these concentric rings called tracks.
And then each track consists of a, it consists of sectors which contain the data.
So typically, 512 bits.
or I'm sorry, bytes.
And then these tracks are separated by gaps that go, that these gaps, like right here, that don't contain data.
Now, platters are aligned on top of each other, on top of each other, on top, on this spindle.
And so tracks that are aligned on the different surfaces, such as this track here, those, the collection of those tracks form what we call a cylinder.
Okay, because it has this cylindrical shape.
Now the capacity of disks is that the number of bits that can be stored.
And vendors kind of, they, all, all disk vendors use, they use, they quote the capacity in
in gigabytes, but where a gigabyte is 10 to the 9th bytes, right, instead of 2 to the 20th, okay, like, like you would expect.
So what, it, I'm not sure why they do this, but it allows, by, by, by quote,
their capacity in gigabytes in 10 to the 9th bytes, it's a bigger number, right?
So it looks better.
It looks like there's more information.
It's a little, I don't really know why they do it, but I think that's why it is.
And it's, so it's one of those little bit annoying things that we just have to just know about and get used to.
Now, the capacity is determined by two independent technology factors.
factors. One is the recording density, so that's how many bits can you pack
you pack into a single sector or a or at least a portion of the track. And then the
track density, which is sort of how close can you put those tracks together. And then the
product of those two is what's called the aerial density and that determines the
overall capacity of the disk. So the higher the aerial capacity, the more bits
you can squeeze onto that, onto that surface. Now, in the old days, when aerial densities were
fairly low, each track on the surface would have the same number of sectors. Okay, so
there was a constant number of sectors per track. So now what happens as you, as your tracks go
from the, you know, near the hole by the spindle as they go, as they move outward.
Right? If you have the same number of sectors with the same, with the same, with the same track, bit density, the gaps between sectors are going to get bigger and bigger as you go out, and you're going to be wasting more and more of your space.
So at, when aerial densities were fairly low, this was okay. But after a while, it just became not okay to waste that much room.
So what modern systems do is they partition the tracks into these so-called recording zones, where each recording zone, such as this right here, each recording zone has a constant number of sectors.
So each track in a recording zone has the same number of sectors.
And of course, as you move outward, if you move outward in the recording zone, you're going to have bigger and bigger gaps.
gaps but then you start a new recording zone that will have more sectors per track.
And then within that, so you can see in this outer, in this outer zone, you have more sectors than
you do on this inner zone. Okay, so that's a way to kind of deal with that, sort of that, that
that growth in the gaps, to keep it from getting too large. And so because we don't really
have the number of sectors per track isn't constant. We'll use the average,
the average sectors per track across all recording zones when we do sort of our capacity
estimates. Okay, so as you can imagine, the formula for computing the disk capacity is fairly
straightforward. It's the number of bytes per sector times the average number of sectors
per track, times the average number of tracks per surface, times the number of surfaces per
platter times the number of platters per disc.
Okay?
Now let's look at how disks work.
So these surfaces are spinning at a fixed rotational rate.
Now, a typical rate, maybe 7,200 r pms is a fairly common rotational rate.
So the disc is spinning around.
You can see this, I'm pretty proud of that, but.
So it's spinning around counterclockwise.
And then the, the arm moves radially.
Here we go. The arm moves radially and it can go over any of the tracks.
Okay. All right, that's enough.
Okay. Now when you have multiple platters, each one of these, each one of these, there's actually multiple arms and there's a reed right head on each surface.
So if the platter has two, if two, if each side of the platter is coated with this magnetic material, then
you have a reed right head on each side.
And then these are all connected and they kind of move together.
Now, originally, these read right heads would be, they were rigid, right?
Because the densities, track densities weren't that high.
So they could, they could just sort of, like, and even though the tracks didn't align perfectly,
they could just sort of, they could, they could still cover the, the reed right heads could still cover the tracks
with these fixed arms.
But nowadays that the densities are so high
that they actually, the controller can actually move the reed right heads
a little bit so that it matches up with all of the tracks
on all of the surfaces.
Okay, so let's look at how this works, how we read data.
So we have our, this is our arm and the tip of the arrow
is the reed right head, and it's positioned, and the platter
is rotating counterclockwise.
And it's positioned just ready to read the blue sector.
So as the blue sector spins underneath the read right head,
it senses those bits and sends them up to the controller,
which passes them back up to the CPU.
And now the CPU is requested that the disk,
it's requested the red data from the red sector.
So we have to take, the controller takes that read right head,
moves it back to red,
moves it back to red's track and then waits for it to spin around and to the read
right head and then it reads that red that red sector.
Okay, so when we first, so there's really three components going on here that determine
how long it takes to read one of these sectors.
The, when we moved the head, that's called a seek.
When we waited for the red track to sort of
rotate around, that's called the rotational latency, so however long it takes, on average it'll be half of the, half of the, half of the time it takes for the entire, to circle all the way around.
And then there's the data transfer, which is sort of how long it takes for that track to pass under the reed right head.
Now the reason, the reason it's important to know this is that these three components, you add them together, and that's the, that's what your average
time it takes to access data.
That time is dominated by the seek time.
So seek times are measured in milliseconds, right?
So we're moving this head.
There's this, there's a servo that has to fire up,
and there's actual mechanical motion.
And that takes time.
And it's on the order of three to nine milliseconds.
And this has been true for decades, right?
So this value is not changing, right?
There's just sort of fun.
fundamental mechanical limits that make it very difficult to decrease this value.
Now the rotational latency, the time that it takes to spin around, we'll call that the T average
rotation, and then the time it takes to read the bits, we'll call T average transfer. Okay, so
we have T average seek, which is this seek time, rotational latency.
and transfer time.
And now if we just take some typical numbers
and plug those in, you see that our seek time is on the order of milliseconds.
The rotational rate is also on the order of milliseconds, right?
So there's also mechanical limits and how fast you can spin these around.
The access time and the transfer time is very small.
So it's orders of magnitude, smaller, because you just have to read a
a few, the bits that are in one sector.
Okay, so if you, if you look, you can, you can see that the total access time is dominated by seek and rotational latency.
So, you know, a good rule of thumb just for sort of estimating how long it takes to read from a disk is just take twice the seek, the seek time, and you'll be pretty close.
And basically the transfer time is you get that for free.
Now here's the, here's the important thing to know about disks.
S-RAM access times about 4 nanoseconds to get a double word.
DRM is about 60 nanoseconds.
So DRAM is about an order of magnitude slower than S-RAM.
But disk is 40,000 times slower than S-ram.
So that's 4,000 orders of magnitude difference.
That's huge.
And it's 250 times orders of magnitude slower than D-Rams.
than DRAMs. So there's a big gap between DRAM and SRM and there's an even bigger gap between
disk and other memory types. Now, modern disks present a much simpler view than this track-cylinder
sector geometry. So modern disk controllers actually present
to the CPU, they present the disk as a sequence of logical blocks where each block is a multiple of a sector size.
So in the simplest case, a block is, just think of a logical block as one sector.
And then blocks are numbered starting at zero, and they just go all the way up to some large number.
And then the disk controller keeps the mapping, maintains the mapping between logical blocks and the actual physical sectors.
So as in the old saying,
is most interesting ideas in computer science involve some form of indirection.
So this is a level of indirection that provides, you know, this mapping between logical blocks and physical
blocks.
So it allows disc controllers to take some cylinders and reserve them as spare cylinders that aren't mapped
to any logical blocks.
And then if there's, if one of the sectors goes bad in a cylinder, the disc controller can just copy the
over to a spare cylinder and then just keep going.
So this, and so this is why your formatic capacity is less than sort of the, you know, if you
you counted the number of actual cylinders on the disk, your formatic capacity is less than the maximum
capacity because some of those cylinders are being reserved for failures.
Now, devices like disks are connected to the, to the CPU and the memory via the I.O.O.
bridge over another kind of bus called an I. This, this, what I'm showing
you, what I'm showing you now is, is actually not representative of modern systems. It's
representative of what was called the PCI bus about five years ago. Modern buses
now are, the PCI bus is a broadcast bus, meaning it's just a single set of wires.
So if any device changes the values on those wires,
every device on that bus can see those values.
That's called a broadcast bus.
And it's the simplest kind of way to hook things together.
Modern systems use a bus structure called PCI Express,
which, although it has the word PCI and it's completely different, it's point to point.
So devices are connected by a set of point-to-point connections
arbitrated by some kind of a switch.
And we won't go into it.
It's the same.
idea it's a much more efficient design it's much faster and but it provides the same
capability mainly it just attaches it allows you to attach all of your devices to your to
your to your to your CPU so just think of this bus as this sort of a single set of
wires where each wire carries a bit and every device attached to it can see
all the values of all the wires and so it there's some devices that
that are just built it directly into the motherboard and they attach to the bus.
Like, you know, disks are just plugged directly into sockets on a motherboard and, you know, your graphics
adapter and the USB controller.
And then the system presents an interface so you can plug mouse, things like mouse and keyboards
into the USB controller.
And then there's expansion slots that allow you, that are connect to the wires in the bus that
allow you to add other devices like maybe network, you know, if you want to put a network
adapter in there. Now what happens when we want to read a disk sector? Well the CPU
initiates this read by writing a triple. So it writes three different values. It writes a
command, like say read. It writes a logical block number. So I want to read a logical block
number. And I want to place the contents of that logical block at a certain
address in memory. Okay, so it's a command, logical block number,
and a memory address.
The disk controller reads the whatever sector corresponds to that logical block.
So we'll assume that logical blocks are consists of one sector.
And then it does this interesting thing.
It copies, it takes control of the bus, and it copies the data, this is the disc controller now,
copies the data across the IO bus through the IO bridge and directly to main memory without ever
notifying the CPU.
So the CPU is completely oblivious to the fact that this transfer is going on.
And then once it's, once it's transferred the data to main memory, then it notifies the CPU using this mechanism called an interrupt.
So it actually asserts a pin on the actual CPU chip itself.
So it changes the value of that pin from zero to one.
And that triggers an interrupt, which notifies the CPU that chip itself.
that that sector's been copied.
Okay, so then the CPU, there's some program somewhere waiting for that data to be read into memory.
So now the CPU can, now the CPU can execute that program and deal with that memory.
So what this mechanism allows, and the reason they do this is because disks are just
just so god-awful slow. The, within 10 milliseconds, a system allows, and the reason they do this is because disks are just so god-allful
slow. Within 10 milliseconds, a system could be executing millions and millions of instructions.
The CPU could be executing millions of millions of instructions. It will be a terrible waste if the CPU
waited for that data to come off the disk. So what it does is it, it issues this request to the
disk controller. And then while that, while that really slow, laborious process is going on,
the CPU can be executing other instructions and doing other useful work.
So this is really essential to sort of getting reasonable performance and from keeping this really slow disk system from slowing the system down.
Now, there's another interesting high kind of disk called a solid state disk, which is kind of halfway between rotating rotating disks and DRAM memories.
And a solid state disk to the CPU, it looks exactly.
like a rotating disk. It has the same socket, it has the same physical
interface, it has the same packaging. It looks like a rotating disk.
But instead of having all these mechanical parts, it's actually built entirely out of flash memory
and firmware that access the controller.
So inside of a solid-state disk, there's a firmware, a set of firmware called the flash translation layer.
translation layer which serves the purpose as the same purpose as the
disc controller does in a rotating disc the and then the memory itself the read
data can be read read read read read and written from the flash memory in units of pages which
depending on the technology can be 512k bytes to 4k bytes and
then a sequence of pages forms a block now these these these these these these blocks
are different from the logical blocks that the CPU does. So it's kind of an unfortunate
overlap of terms. But the trick is, or the, I guess the limitation is that data is written in units
of pages, but a page can only be written after the entire block has been erased.
Okay, so that's, that seems kind of weird, but that's the way it works. So what
that means is if you want to write, if you want to write, if you want to write to a page,
you have to find a block somewhere that's been erased.
You have to copy all of the other pages in your target block over to that new block, and then you can do the write.
Okay, so you can see that writes now become fairly complex operation.
Reads, you can read anything.
And then, like, like, all flash, so it's kind of inefficient, right, because you're writing one page.
But to do that, you have to sort of copy all the other pages in that block, and you have to,
erase the whole, and then when you finish, then you erase this block so it can be used
for for other rights. So eventually, after 100,000 repeated rights, these wear out. Now, the flash
translation layers in modern systems do all kinds of fancy proprietary algorithms to sort
of extend the life. They use caching and various tricks to extend the life of these SSDs. So
in practice, it's not really a problem.
which I'll show you in a second.
So the performance characteristics of SSDs.
Now you can think of a typical hard drive, you might be able to get, you know, I mean, when I measure them,
when I measure my drives, I'm maybe 40, 50 megabytes per second, that would be a typical rate.
Okay, these SSDs are 10 times faster than that.
So for sequential reads, you can get about 550 megabytes, um, sequential rights are a little
bit slower. Random access, whether you're reading or writing, is a little bit slower
slower than sequential access. And as we'll see, this is fairly common. In memory systems, it's almost
always better to do things sequentially than to jump around. And erasing, random rights are slower
because erasing takes about a millisecond, right? So now we're back up to that that millisecond range,
which is slow.
And as I mentioned, if you modify one page, you have to, all the other pages in that block have to be copied.
Now, earlier SSDs had a huge gap between random writes and, uh, and, and, uh, and, and sequential reads.
Uh, but they, because of sort of improvements in the flash translation layer,
these aren't really that, that difference, right?
Reading and writing, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
writing is slower, but they're doing all kinds of interesting, amazing things to get these numbers fairly close.
Okay, so our, when we have a model of SSDs, we really don't need to distinguish anymore that between reads and writes.
Okay, so SSDs, because they have no moving parts, they're faster, they take less power, they're more rugged,
you know, which is why they're good for thumb drives and, you know, iPods, and things like that.
But they have this potential to wear out, which could be a problem, but in practice it's not.
For example, Intel guarantees that you can do 128 petabytes of writes before your SSD is no longer good.
So that's a lot of data to write.
I mean, think about how many years it would take to write that much data.
And as of 2015, as of now, they're a lot more expensive per byte than rotating than rotating disks.
So rotating disks are much bigger, but they're slower.
SSDs are smaller and they're faster.
Now, if you take, if you look at the performance characteristics of these different storage devices relative to CPU,
over time, you get this really interesting graph.
Now, this graph shows on the y-axis access time in nanoseconds in nanoseconds in a log scale.
Okay, so each one of these, each change in units, like from 1,000 to 10,000, represents
a order of magnitude difference in axis time.
On the x-axis, I've plotted time, going from 1985 to 2015.
And then I've plotted the sort of the axis time or the cycle time of the,
the axis time of the, the axis time of the, uh, these devices, these devices,
SSD, DRAM, and the cycle time of processors.
So let's look at, on the bottom, we have the cycle time of processors over time.
And what you see is it's going down at this sort of exponential rate from 1985 to 2003.
There's a doubling basically every 18 months or two years in in clock frequency and a
resulting halving of the cycle time.
over this 18 month or two year period.
So this, so what, what manufacturers did until 2003, to make their processors faster, to make their processors
faster was they would just double the clock frequency.
They decreased the feature size of the chips that they were making, and that would allow
them to put things closer together and then have the, and then increase the, and then increase
the clock frequency by a proportional amount.
Now this all ended, 2003 was an interesting year in computer history because of this,
of this, there's this sort of unfortunate property that the power that you consume is
proportional to your frequency. Okay, so the more power, I mean the higher the
frequency, the more power you consume. By 2003, the processor that Intel was getting
ready to ship was going to burn about 800 watts of power.
Think about 800 watt light bulbs inside your laptop. And I actually saw an early prototype of one
of these devices and the heat sink to absorb the power from the chip was about this big. It
was about four square inches. It was a giant thing just sitting on the motherboard. So that's
What we say is that processor design hit the power wall in 2003.
They could no longer just continue to increase clock frequencies to get faster, to make faster computers.
And what, so what they had to do after 2003, instead of increasing the clock frequency, instead
instead of doubling the clock frequency, they put more processor cores onto the chips
the chips. So now they subdivided a CPU chip into individual
processor cores. Each one could execute its own instructions. Okay. And then, so, and by
running in parallel, you could do more effective work. So the effective cycle time
could continue to go down. So what I've, what I plotted here on the bottom is the
effective cycle time. So basically the cycle time divided by the number of cores. So here in 2005, the
the first systems use two cores. So now you can run two independent threads or two
independent programs. And currently it's about four cores, server class systems. You can get
eight cores. And there's even some 12-core chips. So in the future, what's going to happen
is that the clock frequencies are going to stay fairly constant. So you can see the cycle
times, they actually increased a little bit here. And then they're slowly going down, but
It's generally flat. And so the only way to really get more performance going forward
is to increase the number of independent cores. And that's just, that's just the way it's got to be.
Now here in the black circle, the second line, I've plotted the access time for S-RAM over time.
And you can see that S-RAM is tracking CPU pretty good. And it's, it's an order
magnitude slower, but it's tracking the CPU performance.
pretty well. DRAM, you can see there's a huge gap between the CPU and
the DRAM, several orders of magnitude. And in the last few years, DRAMs have gotten a
little better, but they've proven surprisingly difficult to make faster. SSDs are kind
of in between disks and DRAMs. And then disks up here, you can see at a million
nanoseconds, that's the, that's a millisecond. So you can see disks are sort of in this, in this
sort of millisecond range with access times.
And those, they've gone down a little bit, but not really too much.
So the point I want to make is that there's this huge gap between DRAM, SSD, disk, and CPUs.
And in some cases, it's even getting worse as time goes by.
So that's a problem, right?
How?
Our programs all need data.
Our data is stored in memory and disk.
So if our computer
are getting faster and our storage devices are staying relatively the same or relatively
slower, then we've got a problem, right? Increases in our computer performance won't, it'll be hard
to make our programs run faster because we'll be limited by the time it takes to access
the data. Okay, so that's sort of the fundamental problem that we have to deal with.
And it turns out that the key to bridging this, this gap between the CPU,
and memory is this very basic fundamental property of programs called locality.
Okay? And so this is an essential sort of fundamental enduring property of programs.
So we say that, so programs have this property called locality, and what this means is that, I'm sorry,
I'll just, I have to read it because it because it's really accurate definition. So programs tend to use data and
instructions whose addresses are near or equal to those that they have used recently.
Okay, so if a program accesses a data item, the chances are very high that it's going to access that data item or a nearby data item
or a nearby data item sometime in the near future.
Okay.
That likelihood that the program is going to access that data item or a nearby data item in the near future is this property called locality.
So.
We typically distinguish two different kinds of locality.
Temporal locality is the property that recently referenced items are likely to be referenced
again in the near future.
Okay.
So if you read a variable, chances are you're going to read that variable again.
For example, suppose you're summing into a variable inside of a loop.
Each loop iteration, you're going to access that variable.
Okay.
Spatial locality is that the ten-
for items with nearby addresses that items, if we access one item, chances are
high, chances are high, we're going to access a nearby item. Okay. So let's look at this little
snippet of code and see if we can identify all the different kinds of locality in this code.
So we have two different kinds of references. There's data references, and then there's instructions,
right? So we're reading instructions out of memory, and those instructions are referencing data.
data.
Okay?
So first of all, notice that we're referencing the elements of an array in succession.
So we're increasing I by one each time, and then we're, so we're incrementing I each iteration
through the loop and we're reading AI.
Okay, so this is called a stride one reference pattern.
The stride is how much we're incrementing this index.
So we're, since we're incrementing it by one, we call that a stride one pattern.
So what is how much we're incrementing it by incrementing this index.
What kind of locality is the repeated references to AI? Spatial or temporal?
Spatial, right? Because we're accessing nearby items. Okay, what about referencing this variable sum inside the loop?
That's temporal. Now what about instructions? So we're referencing, each loop iteration we're
referencing, we're executing a sequence of instructions. So what kind of locality is that?
within each loop iteration.
No, that's spatial, right? Because we're just executing a sequence of instructions
within each loop iteration. But then we cycle through the loop repeatedly.
So we'll chances, so each loop iteration, we're going to access each of those instructions
that we access the previous loop iteration.
Right? So we go up and we just keep, we're just going to keep executing the same assembly language instructions that implement this loop body.
Now, in this simple example, it's probably the same.
simple example it's probably this one instruction but in general your
loop can have multiple instructions now what I claim to you I'm one of the one of
the main sort of points of this this this whole course is that as a professional
programmer it's an essential skill that that you be able to look at code and
get a qualitative sense of its locality because as we'll see good locality turns
into good performance the way that systems are built these days.
So as a programmer, it's very important for you to be able to kind of look at code and get some qualitative
sense. Like, eh, that's pretty good locality. That's terrible locality, right? That's, that's,
and what you want to do is avoid the terrible locality in your code. So let's look at a simple
example here to see what I mean by this. So what I'm doing is I'm taking an array, a two-dimensional
array A with M rows and n columns and within a doubly nested loop iterating on I
and J, I'm summing the elements of that array.
Okay, it seems this is a very simple operation. What could go wrong, right?
So it turns out if you write this code to have bad locality, it'll run order magnitude slower.
So just look at this, if you look at this, do you think this has good locality or
bad locality. Let's look at the, with respect to the accesses of A. Good or bad?
Well, so how is, how is A laid out in memory? It's row-wise, right? So C uses, lays out arrays
row wise. So the first, all the elements of the first row, followed by all the elements of the second
row, followed by all the elements of the third row. Okay, so how are we accessing this array? Look at
we're accessing A.I.J and we're varying J the fastest. So we hold I constant
and then we vary J and then we vary J and then we access all, so we hold the I constant to access row I,
and then we vary J to access all the columns in that row. Okay, so each each iter, and then we
go back and increase I, so now we're accessing the next row. Okay. So if we were to look at the
the addresses of A.I.J, the sequence of addresses that are being read, those
would correspond to a stride one axis, and so we'd be accessing all the elements of A sequentially in order.
Okay, so that's really good spatial locality, right? That's the best you can do.
Now what about, what about, and then we have temporal locality on some, so that's good.
Right, so everything about this is pretty good. So this is the good case.
This is the good case.
Now what about this?
What I've done, I've taken the same program,
and I've just inverted the loops.
So I loop on J first, and then on I, and then I just have the same
inner loop body.
Now what does that do to this, what does that do to the spatial locality
of our accesses of A?
Yes.
Terrible, because it's going, you should be offended when you see this.
This is awful.
But it's terrible, right?
Because.
Look at, so we're, now we're holding J, we're holding J constant, and then we're iterating through the Jth element of each row.
So that's skipping.
We have N, we have N elements in each row.
So we're, we're doing a stride N access through memory.
So we're going like this, and then we're incrementing, then we're looking, then we're incrementing the column by one, and then we're doing this again.
So it's terrible spatial locality.
This is the worst spatial locality.
we could get. Now let's look at a three-dimensional array. And let me ask you the, let me pose
the following question. Can you, based on this sort of qualitative idea that, this idea that, this idea
that you want, you want to try to get a stride one reference pattern. Okay, so how would you
permute these, given this, given this inner body, A-K-I-J, how would you promote these,
these loop indices to give a stride-one reference pattern?
That's right. K-I-J is right. So what in general, what we want to do is we want to go, going from right to left,
we want those indices to be changing the fastest. So we want J, we want K and I to be held constant,
and then we want to change J. Then we want to increment I, and then for that value, those values of
K and I, we want to, we want to sequence through all the values of J again. Okay. Okay. Okay. So,
We've looked at properties of storage technologies, and there's this sort of basic, sort of fundamental
principle that cheaper storage, bigger storage, higher capacity storage is cheaper, bigger storage, higher capacity
storage is cheaper. More expensive storage is smaller, right? Because we just don't have
have enough, we can't spend enough money. There's this gap, there's this gap between our storage devices and the CPU,
that, at least in the case of disks, they're getting bigger, and we have programs
that exhibit locality.
Okay, so these three things, these properties of storage technologies, and properties of our programs,
complement each other in this beautiful way to suggest and inform the design of our storage systems.
And this design is something called a memory hierarchy.
Okay, here's the idea of a memory hierarchy.
memory hierarchy. You layer, instead of a flat memory system, you now, you create your memory
system as a hierarchy of devices, and at the top of the, at the top of this hierarchy, you
have your smaller, faster, and more expensive storage devices. So at the very top, you have
registers which are, which can be accessed within one cycle, right, one instruction, while
all that instructions executing can access read and write into a register.
So registers are at the top of the hierarchy. But because those are in custom silicon, they're
very expensive, right? The fabrication plants to make processors cost billions of dollars.
Okay, so this is the most expensive, and because of that, it's also the smallest. We've only got 16
registers at the top of the hierarchy. Now, below that we put one or more S-RAM memories.
Remember, S-RAM is faster.
it's the fastest kind of memory.
So we put one or more so-called caches,
cache memories built out of S-RAM, in the processor chip itself.
And then, and these caches, because they're made out of S-ram,
they're on the order of megabytes in size.
Okay, they're much bigger than registers, but they're
they're megabytes, okay?
Which, if we look, and then beneath that is our main memory,
which is built out of DRAMs, and those can be gigabytes.
tens of gigabytes on modern systems. And then below that is our local disks.
And we can even have lower layers like web servers that are storing, you know, if we're storing stuff on Google,
that you can think of that as just part of our hierarchy.
Now here's the, here's the key idea in a higher, in a memory hierarchy.
Each level in this hierarchy holds data that's retrieved from the next lower level.
Okay.
So registers hold data that's stored in the L1 cache.
The L1 cache holds data that's retrieved from the L2 cache.
The L3 cache holds data that's retrieved from the L2 cache. The L3 cache holds data that's retrieved from main memory.
Main memory holds data that's retrieved from secondary disk and so on.
Now, as we'll see, the reason memory systems are designed like this is that they, when
you have this kind of system, this, you can access, in general, you can access
your data at the speed of the fastest item in the day, at the top of the hierarchy, so that's
the fastest, but with the cost of the storage at the lower part of the hierarchy.
Okay, so this, this works all because of an idea called caching. So a cache, to a cache, to a
computer scientist is a, it's a smaller, faster storage device that acts as a staging
staging area for the data in a larger, slower device. So just like, like here, you can think
of your main memory is a cache for data that's stored on disk, right? You read memory from
disk and then you store it in main memory. Okay, you can think of the main memory as a
staging area. So once you get the data from the disk, you don't access it again on
the disk, you access it in memory, which is much faster.
Okay, so this idea propagates all the way up the hierarchy.
Okay, so we, you can think of a cache, one way to think of a cache is, imagine your backpack when
you're getting ready to come to school in the morning.
So you're in your apartment, which is kind of far away from school.
So before you come into school, you take items from your house and you put them in your backpack,
right?
Because, and then when, and then you walk to, then you come to school, and if you need those items,
they're in your backpack. You know, if you didn't do that, every time you needed something,
you'd have to walk back home and get it and then walk back to school. So it's, so the idea of caching
is very, you know, it's a very familiar kind of simple notion, but it turns out to be quite powerful,
and it shows up in all parts of computer systems. Okay, so what we say is that for each level
K in the hierarchy, the faster, the faster, smaller device at level K serves as a cache for the
larger, slower device at level K plus one. And remember our levels go from, so L0 is the highest.
So the smallest, lowest level is actually the highest, the furthest up in the hierarchy. And
as we increase the levels, we're going down the hierarchy. Now, why do they work? So this is, this is
a really fundamental idea. They work because of locality. So because of locality, because of locality, programs
tend to access data that's stored at level K, more often than they access data at level
K plus one. Okay, so if we access an item at level K plus one, we can move it up to level K. Chances
are, because of locality, we're going to access it again. Okay, so now we're accessing the data
at level K multiple times at the rate, at the speed of level K, not at the speed of level K plus
So that's the fundamental idea.
And because we're not accessing data at level K plus one, as often,
we can afford to use slower storage devices, which are cheaper.
Okay.
And thus we can make them bigger and cheaper per day.
So what this does is the hierarchy creates a large pool of storage that's roughly about the size of the
size of the lowest level that can be accessed at the speed.
at the speed at the highest level.
All right, let's look at how caching works in a general way.
And then we'll see on Thursday how these hardware cache memories work.
Okay, but like I said, caching is a very general idea that can be applied at all levels in the hierarchy.
So here we have a cache.
So the, in all kinds of, most caches, there's some kind of transfer unit to go from one level to the next.
But at this upper level, we have a, what we'll call the cache, that can hold four blocks.
So our memory, and then at the lower level, we have memory.
And this memory is partitioned into blocks of some fixed size.
That's the way cache is near the upper part of the hierarchy work.
Now, at the lower levels, like if you're accessing,
accessing data, say, from a web server, then the data is partitioned into files typically.
Okay. But at upper levels, the data is partitioned into blocks. So just suppose this is main memory. And
then above that we have a, that consists of a bunch of these blocks. So we just take the memory
and partition into blocks where each block is the same number of bytes. And then data will be transferred
between memory and the cache in block size transfer units.
Okay, so if you need data from the memory, if the cache needs data from the memory, it'll grab a whole block.
And then at any point in time, the cache holds a subset of the blocks in main memory.
Okay, so this this cache is much faster, but it's also much slower.
And because of that, and it's much smaller. I'm sorry, it's much faster, but it's much more
expensive because it's faster it's more expensive and because it's more
expensive it's smaller. Now suppose the cache wants to reference say that the CPU
asks for data that's contained in block 4. So it looks it looks to see if the data
is in the cache it's not. So the cache asks the memory to give it block 4. So that
block is copied from memory into the cache overriding the cache overriding the one of the
existing in this case block 8 it'll overwrite block 8 so now now
now block 4 is is is in our cache now suppose now suppose the CPU asked for some data
that's in a block 10 that gets copied up and and and we overwrite that that
block now the whole idea of storing it in the cache is that we're hoping
that the see the program that's executing on the CPU will reuse one of
those blocks we just spent all the time we went to all this
to copy it from memory to this cache.
And we know that's slow.
So now suppose that the CPU needs some data in block B, in this case 14.
Okay, so it needs, it needs a memory word that's stored, that was originally stored in memory at, in block 14.
Well, now this cache can just return, that's what we call a hit, right?
So the, the block that we access is in, in block 14.
is in the cache.
So that's good.
Hits are good.
Because now we can return that block directly to the CPU,
and this memory is much faster than if we had to go all the way to main memory, to the Dram.
Okay, so the S-RAM, much faster than the DRAM.
So the CPU gets that block 14 much faster than it would have if it had just gone all the way to memory.
Okay, the sort of other, the opposite of a hit is a miss.
a miss. So suppose the CPU asks for block 12, the cache looks for that block,
can't find it, that's a miss. So the cache has to ask that the main memory of the DRAM for
block 12 where it gets copied into the cache and then it can return that. So that takes
longer, right? So the CPU has to wait for that block to be fetched from memory.
And so misses are slow. So hits are good because they're fast. Misses are bad because
they're slow. Now we typically distinguish between several different kinds of
caches. So the first kind of miss is a cold miss or a compulsory miss, which is caused because there's just
nothing in the cache. Initially, caches are empty. They have no blocks. And as we fetch blocks from
the lower level from the next level and put them in the cache, the cache will slowly fill
up with blocks and that will increase the likelihood of hits.
But when the cache is empty, we're going to miss every time, right? So there's just no way to avoid cold
misses. So this is called warming up your cache. So as you load data items into the cache,
initially it's cold, and as you add more items, you're warming it up, meaning that you're
increasing the likelihood of a hit. Now, there's a, there's another sort of symmetric kind
of miss, which is called a capacity miss.
And these misses are due to the fact that the cash is just a certain size, right?
You just can't, in the example we looked at, we only had four blocks.
So if we're trying, if our, if our temporal locality involves eight blocks, you know, say if the loop that we're accessing is accessing elements and array that consists of eight blocks,
there's just not enough room to store eight blocks and have four block cache.
So we're going to get mixed.
We would need a bigger cache to be able to satisfy and store those eight blocks.
And if we had a big enough cash, then we'd get good hit rate, right? If we could store all the blocks in our cash, then we, then the cash could take advantage of the spatial and temporal locality within that program.
So in general, what we call this set of blocks at any point in time when a program is running, we call the set of blocks that are sort of being
over and over again, the working set.
And so your working set, and the working set will change, you know, as you go from loop to loop,
or from function to function, but at any point in time in your program, when you have this idea
of a working set, which is sort of the blocks that you need to have stored in your cache.
Okay.
So when your working set size exceeds your cache size, then you get capacity misses.
There's this other kind of weird miss called a conflict miss.
the conflict miss, which has to do with the way that caches are often implemented.
So the idea is that most caches, especially hardware caches, because they have to be simple.
They have, they limit where a block can be placed to some small set of positions in the cache.
So like one of the simplest models is to just take block I can only be
placed in block I, mod, the cache size.
So in our, that little cache we saw that had four blocks, we would take, we would take block I
from memory and we would stick it at block I mod 4.
So block 0 would go at block zero in our cache, as would block 4, and as would block 8.
Block 9 would go into block 1 in the cache, right? And that's, when that happens, suppose
Suppose we use that model. So we're going to take block I and we're going to put it, we can only place it in the cache at block I mod 4.
Now suppose our, suppose our reference pattern involves, from memory, block zero, block four, and block eight.
It's only three blocks.
So we have, we have enough room in the cache to store those three blocks.
But because of the way we've decided to place blocks, each block will be, will evict.
will be will evict when we access block four it'll go into block zero in the
cache when we access block four in the cache it'll overwrite that block and it'll go
into block zero in the cache and so because of this it's really the the the the access
pattern conspiring with the the algorithm that we're using for placing blocks okay
so because of this we have plenty of room in the cache but because of this sort of the
the access pattern conspiring with the placement algorithm, we get misses every time.
We'll see how conflict, we'll see how conflict versus work in detail when we study caches tomorrow.
So, so this is, these, these caches exist everywhere in the memory hierarchy.
And so all of them are caches of one form or another, right? So you can think of the registers as a type of cache.
What do they cache?
Four or eight byte words.
Okay.
Where is it cached? It's cached right on the CPU itself.
What's the latency? It's instant?
It happens within an instruction.
And then who manages the cache? Somebody has to manage the cache.
When there's a request to load an item from the lower level in the hierarchy,
something has to decide what to do with that.
Where to put it in the cache. That's called managing the cache.
Well, in this case, the compiler manages the cache.
When you compile your C code, the compiler figures out which register
data items from memory are going to go into.
Okay.
So, TLB, this is something, this is a cache that's used in virtual memory.
Then there's these hardware caches called L1 and L2 caches.
So they store 64-by blocks on modern Intel systems.
And they're cached on the CPU chip itself in s-ramps that are built right into the CPU chip chip
chip.
And depending on whether L1 caches,
on core I7s have a latency of four cycles and L2 has a latency of 10 cycles.
And both of these are managed by hardware.
So when you, when the CPU fetches an item from the L1 cache,
hardware finds it and if there's a miss and a block is loaded from L2,
hardware and the L1 cache figures out where to put it.
Okay, so all this is done without any intervention by hardware.
Discs contain buffer, operating systems maintain buffer caches.
So in this case, what's cached is portions of files.
Okay.
And they're cached in main memory.
And latency to main memory is about 100 cycles or so.
And these are managed by the operating system.
So the operating system reserves a portion of memory to store files that you've loaded.
So the operating system exploits locality.
If you read a file and then start reading, referencing bytes from that file, it'll actually be served from the file cache and it won't go out to disk.
Networks maintain caches like things like NFS and AFS maintain local caches on disk.
Your browser has a cache, so when it fetches files from servers, it stores those files locally on disk.
So if you reference those web pages again,
They're served from your local disk rather than going all the way across the network.
Okay, so the point is that these caches exist everywhere in the memory hierarchy.
And they're all based on the same principles.
They're just implemented in different ways.
Okay, so just to summarize what we've done today,
we've seen that there's a gap between the CPU and our storage devices that continues to increase.
We've seen that well-written programs have this property.
property called locality.
And we've seen that caching, by taking, by using caching, we can build a memory hierarchy that takes advantage
of locality and programs and allows us to build storage systems that allows us to build storage systems that
where we can access data at the rate of the fastest device, but at the cost and capacity of
of the devices at the lowest level.
Okay.
So Thursday, we're going to look at a very specific part of the
the hierarchy called cache memories.